seeing God's to rituals would you say
that they are useless in one's life
the ritual
well depends on the purpose
first let's highlight your intentions
say foot towards enlightenment but to
say they're completely useless for an
average person's life that's not true
either in the sense that if there were
no rituals for many people would have no
would have had no sense of routine no
sense of duty or certain like repetition
and then rituals make them stick to it
out of that primordial anxiety and fear
toward you resistance you turn to
rituals and there needs to do them of
course it's fundamentally the wrong view
that's why if you were to use that as a
vehicle for enlightenment it's just
impossible it's actually an impediment
it's actually an impediment
it's a fit
like coming up age rituals different
societies I think it's just symbolism
I think it's just symbolism
or rituals tools are having a shrine
well see now now you're coming into more
specific more specific type and that's
where you have to ask yourself why I
mean cultural sort of systems we chose
into society are part of the culture
there's nothing to do anything it's just
I'd evolved but yeah if you're having
rituals in regard to enshrine you are
sir why is it because you're not
practicing towards the Enlightenment but
then what difference is making a bar to
the shrine
what are you doing with it are you
expecting something to happen to you and
something to be given to you
blessings from something or someone
through your idol worship
and so for somebody who's practicing the
Dharma there really is no room for any
rituals and if you if you keep
maintaining the need of rituals in your
life to that extent you're not
practicing towards the reveal because
you're depending on this external
magical belief
because that's that basically placing
responsibility on the performance of
ritual as opposed to taking up
responsibility yourself in which case
you yeah you feel it very differently
because it's not about where you're
meant to do what what the science have
shown you to do it's what you chose to
do which means any second you can choose
otherwise and you feel that edge but
that's just necessary so if you're
avoiding taking on that kind of weight
of responsibility that's when you sort
of giving input responsibility on to
rituals and to that extent you wanna be
practicing
what about protocols society it's no
other just protocols tonight as empty
motions you go through they don't need
to be in anything you disregard
particulars well if to be careful
because protocols and manners mean a lot
to other people so if you disregard it
you're gonna be the rest that account
which is exactly why there's so many of
those hardware the small smaller rules
there are completely irrelevant to us
affect Sudama but we still have them as
monks because they kind of originated
organically but with interactions with
the society but there's nothing to do
with anything it was just like the
certain norms in that in the current
society they complain about certain
things and yeah the Buddha could have
sort of explained to them that it was
completely wrong in its a wrong view but
he wouldn't have changed much because
people wouldn't have abandoned those
views so then when you look at it
perfectly it only resulted in monks
being caressed and hassled one of kind
of upsetting people that doesn't mean
you don't draw a line when it comes to
Dhamma then you just go with whatever
people deem whether people want to hear
but certain things that are not
impediment to the Dhamma
either way so what do you do it or not
do it makes a difference as you practice
the Dharma but makes the difference for
society you live in then you do what the
site expects you so you'll be left alone
so you can practice in peace but of
course if the society demands you to get
married or something well that's
directly against the practice of Dharma
so you just will never do that even if
the site is very upset
but if the sightly demands you to wear
shoes in town because they can't stand
inside of a barefoot person that's fun
it makes no difference and the only
difference going to be is how much
harassment you're gonna get
whose respect respecting your elders oh
yeah know that that's a bit more you
know there is some meaning behind it you
should respect it because without them
you wouldn't you would be we wouldn't be
where you are and it's respecting elders
in general again it maintains a certain
standard of relationship with others
that then others can learn from if you
start disregarding elders and teaching
others to disregard the elders in here
the value the values of respecting the
others will be eroded doesn't mean you
you agree that elders always know the
best for you even know the best for them
but in the terms of the way you would
relate to another person here you
respect their older and same with monks
in your seniority according to the
original in their seniority is just so
the people will dwell in comfort so we
don't all go at the same time and grab
the pots with food and fight over who's
gonna serve first no certain order means
certain harmony but that's that's as far
as it goes it does not mean that
somebody who's more senior has a say
over you but as I said to tell you what
to do one knows better unless you took
them as a teacher because you do see
that they know more than you do
but in itself as a kind of institutional
order that's it it's it's on a very
worldly level oh you go first cause
you've been here longer better but
doesn't mean that your vote or your safe
weighs more than mine because you've
been here longer
when it comes to dhamma or to the sangha
methods so that's often what we are
guess often gets sort of blurred in
between so by by default but being more
senior means you know more or you
certainly have more say over those who
are not a senior they must do what you
tell them to do simply not the case
unless they took on that relationship of
a teacher in which case a junior person
can be a teacher if he's taken as a
teacher to play with somebody else so
that's a completely different type of
relationship
so when people repel against seniority
that's usually where they repel against
but they don't necessarily see that
because the lines were blurred
they don't rubella they shouldn't be
rebelling against the just a norm of
respecting elders and elders working
first the saw or the once was more
senior but yeah they should repel elders
sort of assuming wisdom just because
they've been here longer and they assume
that they know much more than you do but
even against that you have to repel you
just pay attention
so that your parents aren't exactly the
nicest people exactly we respect them as
your parents but that doesn't
necessarily mean you you you you listen
to them when they tell you what to do
because they genuinely don't have a clue
but they might not have a clue you don't
dismiss it but once you fully understood
but you want to do what you're doing why
it is good and their parents insane
turning you the opposite no you should
get married and have children sup well
you realize that that's ignorant that's
just their craving and desire talking
but you don't disrespect them on account
of it there's no need for disrespect
what type of work should a person do you
what is it
this kind of work
again who are we talking about for late
rapists no no all right well any work
that doesn't go against the 5p6
and what what would you say so the
purpose of your work
I was just sustaining your life
and that's about it you find a certain
you find a certain balance between how
much you you want and how much you
actually need and then you work to meet
your needs and maybe get extra just in
case but you don't work for the sake of
game you can't even possibly practically
benefit from nor can you benefit others
which is when people just just keep
acting out of out of ideals of wealth
and acquiring things well like in
reality you can't even you can't even
use it over so if you have family and
children here that's of course something
you have to work for to support them but
if you don't means you you really have
to work much if you lower your needs and
live simply
so you have to keep your ambition in
check and your cravings till it's gained
towards access to is actually that's
comfort all those things need to be paid
for which means you will need to work
for all those things but
most people end up working for a lot lot
more did they actually even want but
because they never stop and think about
what they actually want let alone what
they really need they just end up going
with a little paying into it more and
being very unhappy encounter because
they didn't they didn't clarify where
the line is for them they didn't draw
them up
wisdom well yeah any any form of
self-reflection is a prerequisite for
wisdom paired with wholesome of course
and there because I'd be lucky boys work
is suffering it is working every day
he's ours day
well the most the most obvious example
is when people start having families era
I have children's own and they don't
really think it through they just act
out of desire to have children creating
a family but they need to know the
weight of responsibility the burden of
work gets in fighting you go one child
to work for you to have to work even
more three four children means a lot
and then we also means that if you don't
have worked if you keep finding
different work means you have to work
for very little because
[Music] leverage you need what you need any form
leverage you need what you need any form
of earning because you have three
children to support but again you can't
blame anybody else for you
avoid shooting the point so one should
avoid work no of course but one
shouldn't be yeah
one shouldn't be known in regard to the
either so that's what I mean there is a
you must work for something well even as
monks that's that's often he was he was
in the suitors like the carpenters they
work with wood the Aerosmith's that make
errors and the monks detained themselves
that practice restraint and that's their
work that's where they get the food and
people give them more friends
so in a way it's it's like the most
wholesome way of transaction so to speak
people by by by making by giving they
make married and also you can learn
Dharma but there is no fixed price as in
you have no wage so sometimes you might
not get anything sometimes you might get
too much
so you're just sort of but that's not
your concern your concern is to do that
work of a month for yourself not for the
game if the game comes to the extent of
having a basic requisites covered yeah
that's fun if it comes more you might
share with other monks that's fine if
not none of it that's also fine
so it's not that different when somebody
works for a wage okay I'll do this you
pay me this much just it's more
wholesome in the way because people who
just donate but the principle is the
same whatever you do you have to work to
a degree or something so the point is
that most people in the world not of the
monks they don't they don't think
through what they want in their life
what they need in their life so then
they just end up like everybody else
just going with the sensuality with the
central desires and there is no end to
amount of how much you will need when it
comes to senses because those those
desires are insatiable so the more you
want the more you will need so that's
why people don't think it through then
of course I won't I want to go out I
want to go and holiday I want this I
want this I want excitement I want fun
and if money for it so I must work I
must work a lot I must work too much but
if you stop and think about is it really
worth working that much just for this
fleeting excitement that you get through
through spending their money in central
enjoyment and probably about the third
2/3 of people would be would be quite
happy they scale back onto the the
amount of work they now must do but in
order to be able to scale back they also
have to then lower a bit of their
desires and cravings in regard to
which is not hard thing to do if you
start thinking about it most people
don't even think about and that's what
most people get end up being overworked
and stressed overly stressed and
generally not happy
this is suta from the NBA
I'll just read out first
wave was sick the question about one
concise statement about one an
explanation of one
with reference to what one says when a
bigger is completely disenchanted with
one thing completely dispassionate
toward it completely liberated from it
completely sees it's delimitations
and completely breaks through its
meaning in this very life becomes he who
makes an end of suffering what one thing
all beings exist through neutral understanding that
understanding that
understanding the principle of
dependence the principle of depending on
the nutrient
it still fits
as same time yeah little bit but it's
about it in the most most precise understand
the second second one is a question
about two concise statement about two
and explanation of the team so the same
thing
we need to become to complete
disenchanted with these two things he
makes me to suffering let's name and
form
in the third well it's everything that
appears its name
the third one is what threes we can to
feeling great so it's getting a more
specific
most fundamentally understand the
principle of potato bother the principle
of nutriment the principle of
simultaneous dependence with the
presence of a nutriment this is present
the new tourism there this cannot be
either so that dependent of it you don't
necessarily go and investigate the
content of nutrient you you look at the
principle of dependence upon a new claim
so that is a pretty much the most
fundamental thing
which is why the Buddha said the one who
sees Patito bodices the Dhamma
maybe circuits edit
and then if you don't see it on that
fundamental level well you can see it on
another almost as equally fundamental
which is the name and form the die at
the two and it did everything that you
can conceive of it's with the name of
form there's no outside of it there's no
there's no behind it you can also be
aware of that does not be taken and
whatever you can be aware whatever you
can be conscious of in the most remote
peripheral ambiguous sense it's within
them form it's the name before
whatever has a nature to appear no
matter how subtly it's the name form so
if you understand the principle of
appearance is in the principle of the
name and form of their diet you've
understood everything if you display the
experience this passion towards it
disenchantment does the various project
now if you if you fail to see it and
then level ready have another chance of
in regard to the three types of feelings
because that's another point of
convergence so to speak it's an
it's an
it's on the level of how you feel so the
level of how you feel that's where you
create that's why you create that's - -
not understanding the feeling so by
understanding the principle of cream in
regard to 3000 feeling by experiencing
dispersion in regard to three types of
feeling disenchantment you are
completely free all the things resolved
in the same just how
the difference is hard deeply
understanding sort of collaboration
propensity but it doesn't matter even if
it's not to the most fundamental level
as long as the same principle of
dispassion is developed in regard to the
relevant things that's all it matters
the first one all beings exist
to neutral
[Music] so how do you do
just Conte to
your existence is dependent on food well
yeah you can you can say that but
obviously you want to you don't as I
said you want to be just looking at the
particular content of that nutrient you
want to be looking at the principle of
dependence so you can say your life
depends on eating food now there are
many different things within that they
can be standing for the same principle
such as having the healthy body
that can still purchase in they're just
having your intestines were working
properly having the right hormonal balance and
having the right hormonal balance and
everything else because if any of those
things get messed up you won't be able
to be well the food won't be making much
difference to
all you can be very healthy but if there
isn't a suitable food say so the
nutrient the principle nutri means
depending upon something you in your
core depending upon something that is
not yours that cannot be yours like you
can be occurring all the food you want
but we have no say over their molecular
operations of your organs whether they
are still healthy whether they are still
absorbing things correctly or you're
having some some disease growing in you
or cancer that again it's going to
render the body useless so no more of
good and healthy food will make you live
anymore so that's what I mean you have
to you have to discern their dependence
in your core not like explain it in a
medical or scientific or psychological
manner saying yes food results in this
you'll see that this you start with this
which is you are the present experience
as a whole within that in its heart
there is a dependence upon things that
are not in your control that's in the
heart of your very being so you don't
start by work you don't start from there
you don't start from the start you have
to reverse back into the into the the
correct understanding of a foodie so you
don't start like food makes me this will
you start with this depends on food so
if the complete is the opposite
direction because because it's true yeah
the food makes you alive makes you
healthy makes everything but that is
that is not seen in that personal manner
and you are not seeing the principle of
their personal dependence you're just
explaining to yourself sort of your body
works when it comes to food and
but that's not the inside that's an
explanation in order to see their
dependence you start with what you have
which is this body here but whatever it
is healthy or partially healthy or sick
doesn't matter the center of the
universe that is your center of the
union that you believe that's your point
of view that's your that's your
situation that's your world as the
Buddha said there is no world outside of
this body less than less than two meters
tall that's say the whole universe is
that's say the whole universe is
contained within it it's knotted so
metaphysical sense is just exactly no
matter how far you travel you it eats
through your body that you get to
experience the world so the body is your
world so you have to start with that and
then with it without abandoning that
without jumping back onto to
psychologizing or explaining it within
your situation of your body of your of
your present experience as such you try
to discern within that the dependence on
the phenomenon of nutrient of support
different than itself that's a
definition of a nutrient we don't
actually contemplate the food conference
great no you just look at the principle
of dependence so that's the definition
that's why the nutriment understanding
the nutriment mean understanding the
principle of dependence so this is your
entire world that's all you can ever
have you can't step outside of it and
you see that in its heart depend upon
the whole domain of things that cannot
be controlled by this domain of my body
so in that sense you see that your whole
life depends upon something else that
it's not in your control
not yours thank you
cannot be but you can be you can be
ground you can be as I said you can be
collecting in and holding up all the
foods you'll never go hungry but that's
that's aiming it at a different level
and the wrong level because it doesn't
matter how much you have or how much you
don't have what matters is that you can
not change the fact that you depend on
it that's the main point so you can have
all the food for the rest of your life
never to go hungry that again that
doesn't bring you any closer towards
understanding the nature of depending
upon food in the first place whether you
have the food or not has nothing to do
with it it has to do with depending upon
that which is not you which cannot be
which cannot be assimilated into you and
it's not incidental that eating sort of
mirrors that principle of a simulation
of possession because you're trying to
regain the control of your very being
through eating that's or any form of
sensuality ends up being manifested as
consuming visually audibly affected and
so try to take try to repossess it that
upon which you actually depend which
means you can only repossess the content
of something but the principle of your
dependence remains completely intact it
cannot possibly change and fully
understanding that means full
understanding but it's a bother
now how you choose to describe it is in
bada and how many factors and so on
that's actually relevant or not as
relevant the relevant is the product by
the we'll also talk about a nutrient
contract is a nutrient for the feeling
and so not necessarily just the food the
physical food he's talking about
dependent upon support but
simultaneously being determined as you
are by something that you're not well
the functioning body is just and
completely always as always as always
has to be present and it's completely in
septums completely inseparable from and
you know saying that you have no say in
its dependence on further food and so on
yet your whole life stands upon it so
that's not something you have to you can
only figure out once you have to keep
drilling and drilling and repeat in
those those contemplations because if
you're doing that you keep removing
layer by layer of it that you create it
or ignore it
thank you buddy yeah the body is mind
and body it's foolish that said I'm
eating the food three four I have the
food I don't have the food that's what
many people would be so afraid to just
go hungry even for the day you start
experiencing genuine anxiety just not
not that you are starving which is for
missing a dinner for example let's all
assumption consumption
assuming it worked what assumption gives
the range for your consumption
that's what sensuality is an assumption
this is the extent and that was
determined by the assumption that were
assumption determines the borrower
determines the bead and now your
consumption is sort of engagement
without extent with that being so you
consume because you are seeing here you
assume that you can consume you assume
that when you eat food you really
assimilated it in you but you didn't
that food was external to the point of
view when he was on the table
and it's equally external when it's in
this stomach because the stomach in the
table are on one plane and your point of
view is on the other if there is any
distinction is that it's not like my
stomach is in and the table is outside
anything physical is outside including
eating food is still physical and it's
our time
so you're dependent on the nutriment
means dependence on that external form
that you require it to be present and
you have no sane as I said you can be
controlling all the food production and
have everything and then monitor your
health and you still will get sick and
you will die between this fundamentally
you cannot have a say in it it has its
own course it has its own domain and its
impermeable to you and to your effort
into your internal cycles taking it in
you when you start looking backwards there
when you start looking backwards there
is a reasonable place that you can take
it in - no there is no inside that's it
that's all for another ham has fully
removed the slightest traces of those
assumptions there is this body this
conscious body left and named inform
externally there is no more assumption
of internal to him wrestle me but find
no form doesn't find the footing in the
consciousness yeah sure the foot that
form is the internal they assumed
internal in me like I am this barrier
and this is outside and this isn't me so
by having it taking it in but when you
start looking you realize oh there is no
external and internal I mean you can
designate it whichever way you want but
it's how you relate to it usually
internal it's related to his mind me
within me but if you start looking at it
in that dispassionate manner correctly
in the right order or first with your
situation within that the dependence of
that situation put something that
simultaneously there that cannot be
yours then you start seeing there is no
external and eternal that is just
external and slightly less external and
no matter how far internally you look
it's equal external as in it pertains to
the external domain it's just closer to
you so to speak but before with that
assumption of extent if it's if it
passes that extent then it's in you
created that internal dimension of mine
that's it so yeah of course can I see
yeah and that's that's when it ceases to
be the self it loses that dimension of
mine it ceases to be out of order
because again that's why also heart of
others the assumption for self
independent of the 500 independent of
the experience as a whole you assume
this great think that's outside of it as
in that it's all of this is within it
all of this is in me for me it's mine so
all those things all those things are
really revolving around the same
principle and listening industry is
infinite yes well I mean in you can you
can endlessly assume particular or you
can endlessly engage with your
assumptions but of course assumptions
will come within the certain domains
assumption sensuality assumption of
views assumption of virtue and duty
holding onto and so on
consumption of being
try to consume you
assumption is basically maintaining the
view of an extent
despite things within their extent
proving you wrong going otherwise or
being otherwise in nature like
sensuality for example assumption of
sensuality is assumption of extent of
attractive yet in practice that is
always contradicted by the by the by the
repulsive heart of anything central
and also parts so if you start seeing
that your assumption sensuality is
inseparable from that which is repulsive
inconceivable apart bound up with it
cease to be attractive so your essential
sumption is faded without anything being
changed so to speak all those things
still remain they used to attract you
that used to they used to incite you but
now that incitement and desire is gone
but all those things stay because there
were never the problem it was you
assuming a wrong extent in regard to
them you giving them the attractive
being through that assumption
they were attractive could you kept
assuming them as attractive because you
could not see their nutritional
dependence upon that which is inherently
the parcel physical body food liquids
smells anything
or just generally permanence and lack of
control aging sickening dying sentient
is inseparable from any sexuality even
refines is rather unnecessary just cause
sexuality or or or gluttony but you know
a refined sense of smell
it can even be worse for people because
if they don't see that as equally potato
to a sensual domain they'll they won't
see where the work is
they won't see where the problem is
so assumption by its definition means
taking up for granted so this has
appeared seemingly attractive and you
just took it at a face value and then
started pushing that extent of
attractive work infinitely but then if
you start to reverse-engineer it while
its presence are seen what's behind it
that keeps determining the extent of
your assumption you realize it's the
repulsive it's that which I cannot
control I can no say in it no amount of
beauty can be independent of the of the
material foam being present and as such
the material form is completely
subjected to elements and everything is
that you can't even conceive accessing
and controlling let alone having is
yours and it's simply by not thinking
about that you maintain the the
assumption of sensuality and the whole
extent proliferating except if you start
thinking about it that's how you start
draining draining those those those
unwholesome floods the answers you don't
just shut off and suddenly stops you
ejected to find the source and then
drain it from the source
dry it up and then it'll it will
evaporate everywhere else
and try to
assuming something else
beyond everything to see say
consciousness Oh God
Oh God
it's just a way of trying to
gain poultice
it is usually the people's views of God
is just extension of themselves the self
mastery of everything including yourself
science science it's basically a new
religion for many people it's this
external externally adopted view that
you cannot have from your point of view
you can only keep assuming it as
something that you can have that's why
the you Padano of the views the
assumptions of the views
some meditators for
you catch the right moment or witness
witness the atoms and so it's a
completely the wrong direction if
anything you want if any if you want to
focus on anything it should be the
background of whatever was present but
if you see you can't focus on that in
the same sense than you used to focus it
you can't concentrate on that at one
point you know when when the suitors
talk about one pointedness people
usually people usually assume is
actually you get so absorbed in one
point did everything else stops
bothering but it's completely overrun
you step back into such a general point
that everything is included with it
within it so nothing can bother you
that's why that's all again like what's
in common to everything that that you
can for example see visually or
experience through senses well it's the
four Great elements so that's really
called great elements not because a
particular elements you observe through
a microscope but because you discern the
principle of those elements in
everything that can appear if your mind
gets established upon the principle of
those elements means you have surmounted
anything that's particularly containing
that principle in the same sense the
Buddha would say upon the greater
perceptions of the forest you abandon
perceptions of the village then you
realize that well I can't be bothered by
anything from the village because my
mind is established upon this perception
of the forest you and you're not in the
forest but then I can be bothered upon
the things that can arise in the forest
on those perceptions so then he would go
further and establish his mind even in
an in a greater background of that and
what's the greater background of village
forest it's the earth it's the element
of Earth then he establishes mindfulness
on that refined background I mean you
can see how general that is that for
most people it could really abstract it
makes no sense yet for a trained mind it
can perceive it on that abstract level
and that means it's not abstract and
immoral to proceed right and they're in
there because it is present in their
general sense and if the mind gets
established upon that means nothing can
bother you
the perceptions of the forest let alone
those even more inferior perceptions
that's where the bull was talking about
casinos he was exactly that same
principle or Janus for the matter you
established your mind upon the greater
domain so that the inferior domain
cannot cannot overcome you cannot you
cannot bother you anymore
so the casinos will be the four Great
elements who is there and any of them
can serve doesn't mean you have to go
one two three you take any of it
depending like how capable your mind is
and if you established your mind upon
that right order in terms of their
general and no particular things within
it you have surmounted it and that's
what we would say like now that the mind
is established upon your maneuver
nothing inferior to it can bother me
that Oh is the more can I go even higher
okay then he refines the element then he
goes into the perceptions of colors and
light and so on then the infinite space
and then eventually the casino of
consciousness which is a theme most
refined the utmost netted the utmost
background the art in general and he
says there is no hardness
that's what the seat of consciousness
punched consciousness
it's the ultimate background so to speak
but again if you saw it's the alternate
diagram well that's now a clearly
defined phenomenon a thought Dhamma in
your mind
which means that's not that
consciousness is being aware of the
background to the full extent in regard
to whatever has appeared that's how I
developed the casino consciousness being
aware of the background without falling
into losing mindfulness on account of
being pulled and absorbed into
particular that's why I would always
sort of point out how like a commonly
where people think meditation is in
terms of view and absorption it's a
completely wrong direction you need to
be looking at the background or what's
simultaneously present not keep trying
to catch the right moment within what
singleton what we're willing what's
present right in front of it that all
comes from that projection that you can
witness something outside of yourself
well whatever you're witnessing that's
your perception which means doesn't
matter how far or near you can't
perception is there and you're not
seeing its nature that's why we talk
about the nature of the five aggregates
to be understood not a particular
content that you have to chase down and
catch in documents and witness they will
then do the work for you - intention - intention
neutral
he's right yeah
the nutria phenomena quiz consciousness
as in the nutriment for something to
appear is the fact that it can appear
and the nutrient for consciousness is
nama Rupa as in in order for something
to appear there has to be something
that's that can appear so so that's
that's why the nama Rupa determined by
consciousness consciousness determined
by enamel because if there is nothing to
appear you can't even conceive any
slightest notion of appearance so that's
why there is no consciousness pure
consciousness or pure awareness or pure
presence in itself there has to be
something that is present that's we
fundamentally rule prime Vanara nama
Rupa in vijnana Vignon in nama Rupa and
you don't have to go further than that
either that's when that didn't occur so
I can't remember the number one of the
famous border the good of a posse was
when he was when he was discerning the
principle but it's no bother
he did not go to the usual in the
description that we know of twelve
factors he stopped he said what was
determined by what the term is nama Rupa
oh it's Vinny honor usually then he
would go further what it is vineya now
it's in car about it I'm missing car now
it's ignorance of some car and that's it
the Buddha we passed said what it is now
Rukavina embody time is vini honor oh
it's nama Rupa that's it
either way he cannot own it either way
he cannot take possession of that so if
he looks at vijnana is determined by
nama Rupa so to speak he looks a number
opposite my banana so to speak it's
always outside of his reach the
determination does he fully understood
the principle of the determination the
principle that it some part of the
principle of depending upon something
that it's outside of your reach and
that's how you remove the notion of
ownership which is on the notion of
reach and then he said that he just spent his
and then he said that he just spent his
time then contemplating manifestations
of the five aggregates through that
principle of being fully determined by
that which is outside here is reached
he became some Samba delighted so that's
that's why I always come down to the
principle and that's the difference as
well like the suit that you read when
you say the first the first nutriment
you understand one or you understand the
diet or you understand the three it's
exactly that difference that would have
a past it didn't go to understanding the
one he came to the diet
he understood the principle oh please
don't bother based on it he contemplated
and develop it seen it through and
through and became some example where
the Gautama was the foremost in
formulating the Dharma which means he
was able to discern it up to the fullest
so that's why he would formulate the the
principle of potential bata in all like
like like twelve factors as we know but
it wasn't a rigid thing because there's
a different ways you can describe the
same principle that's when some other
sutras he will be describing but it some
para in sixteen factors but after
feelings and craving people take up with
guns and sticks and fight and so on and
he was part of it but its own bother so
don't think about it is some sort of
determination or chain thing where is a
principle of simultaneous presence and
dependence upon something that you
cannot have
and that's why it directly undermines
the sense of ownership you don't have to
develop a posse or whoever practices
contemplates correctly doesn't have to
sit back and afterwards and then think
how does that prevent him from taking
things as mine understanding that your
sense of self your entirety of your
experience is determined by that which
you cannot have on the same level of
that experience if you look at that then
is determined by the other thing it's
always it's always opposite of where you
look hence I keep talking about
development of mindfulness development
of Samadhi is through discernment of the
background establishment of your mind
upon the background because that's where
the termination is you can't make a
determination in front of you and
examine it it on the same level because
that something else is the background
which means something else determines
that which you're looking at so you stop
had to be you have to cease being
forever focused and concerned with the
content and start discerning the nature
the background the more general and the
Buddha name the entire teaching has the
nature there are all these particular
Dahmer's in my teachings understanding
of their nature understanding of Werdum you